Register of the Howard V. Canan Papers, 1918-1955
Hoover Institution Archives
Howard V. Canan Papers
1918-1955
74032
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize folder, 1 oversize box, 3 envelopes (1.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, orders, reports, speeches, certificates, and photographs, relating to military engineering in the U.S. and in the European Theater during World War II.
Canan, Howard Voorheis, 1894-
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Biographical Note
1894 August 6 Born, Omaha, Nebraska
1918 B.S., U.S. Military Academy, West Point, N.Y.
1919 A.E.F., France and Germany
1925-1928 11th Engineers, Panama Canal Zone
1932-1936 District Engineer, U.S. Lake Survey
1938-1941 War Department General Staff (G-2 Div.)
1943-1946 Office of the Chief Engineer, European Theater of Operations
1946-1949 District Engineer, Nashville, Tennessee
1952-1953 Engineer Inspector General
1953-1954 Assistant Chief of Engineers for Real Estate for Army, Air Force, and Atomic Energy Commission
United States. Army--Officers.; Military engineering.; United States--Armed Forces.; World War, 1939-1945--Engineering and construction.; World War, 1939-1945.
- WAR DEPARTMENT ORDERS AND LETTERS, 1918-1954
  Scope and Contents note
  Orders and letters from the U.S. War Department, relating to the military career of Howard V. Canan
  - 1918-1954 (Box 1)
  - 1946-1954 (Box 2)
- SPEECHES AND ADDRESSES, 1927-1955.
  Speeches, addresses, notes, and miscellaneous speech material of H. V. Canan, arranged chronologically
  - "Art of Command," lecture for non-commissioned officers schools co. "C" 11th Engineers, 1927 (Box 2)
  - "Panama Canal," talk before Kiwanis Club, Golden Colorado, 1930
  - "Expenditure of N.I.R.A. Funds for River and Harbors on Lake Superior," talk for various civic clubs, Duluth, Minnesota, 1933
  - "The U.S. Lake Survey," address before the Federal Business Association, Detroit, Michigan, 1934
  - "Work of the U.S. Lake Survey Office, Corps of Engineers," address before the civil society, Civil Engineering Dept., University of Detroit, 1934
  - "The General Staff Aspects of Tactical Interpretation of Aerial Photographs," presentation of Engineer School, Ft. Belvoir, 1941
  - "The G-Z Interest in Camouflage Activities," presentation for assault course, Engineer School, Fort Belvoir, Virginia, April 15, 1941
  - "The General Staff Aspect of Tactical Interpretation of Aerial Photographs," presentation at Engineer School, Ft. Belvoir, July 8, 1941
  - Talk before members of the Barbourville Chamber of Commerce, Barbourville, Kentucky, December 20, 1946
  - "Report on the Midwest Flood Control Conference, Indianapolis, Indiana," talk given before the Tennessee Conservation Commission, 1947
  - Notes for a talk to be given before the Lions Club of Burnside, Kentucky, February 24, 1947
  - "Highway and Bridge Relocations, Center Hill Dam and Reservoir," an address before the Annual Highway Conference at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, Tennessee, April 18, 1947
  - Talk before the Cookeville Lions Club at the Center Hill Dam and Reservoir, April 21, 1947
  - "Recreational Program of the Corps of Engineers within Reservoir Areas," Cincinnati, Ohio, April 28, 1947
  - "Land Utilization, Center Hill Reservoir," address for the Lions Club, Smithville, Tennessee, May 22, 1947
  - "Center Hill Dam and Reservoir," address before the Carthage Rotary Club at Center Hill Reservoir, May 27, 1947
  - "Center Hill Dam and Reservoir," address before the Cookville Rotary Club at Center Hill Reservoir, May 28, 1947
  - "Flood Control in the Upper Cumberland Valley," Upper Cumberland Flood Control Association, Pineville, Kentucky, July 3, 1947
  - Talk before the Nashville Chamber of Commerce Navigation Committee, August 26, 1947
  - "Dam Construction on the Cumberland River," talk before Engineer Club, September 29, 1947
  - "The Functioning of an Engineer District," presentation for visiting student officers, Nashville, Tennessee, 1948
  - "Work of the Nashville District," address before the Tennessee Military District, February 9, 1948
  - "National Security," talk given before the Rotary Club at Martin, Tennessee, April 7, 1948
  - "Necessity for Timely and Adequate Appropriations of Funds for Major Construction Projects," talk before the Ohio Valley Improvement Association, April 12, 1948
  - Address before engineer aviation group, April 26, 1948
  - Talk before Livingston Rotary Club at Standing Stone Park, April 27, 1948
  - "Land Utilization and Recreational Activities - Wolf Creek Reservoir," address before the Lions Club, Jamestown, Kentucky, May 20, 1948
  - "Functions of the Corps of Engineers in Recreation," talk before the Kiwanis Club of Hartsville, Tennessee, July 2, 1948
  - "Land Management and Recreational Activities on the Wolf Creek Reservoir," address given before the combined Civic Clubs of Somerset, Kentucky, July 15, 1948
  - "Functions of the Corps of Engineers in Recreation," talk before the Rotary Club, Cookville, Tennessee, August 17, 1948
  - "Center Hill Reservoir and Land Utilization," talk before the Chamber of Commerce, Lebanon, Tennessee, October 19, 1948
  - "Address before the Chattanooga Chapter, Associated General Contractors, Chattanooga, Tennessee, October 21, 1948 (Box 3)
  - "Work of the Nashville District," talk before the Reserve Officers of Knoxville, Tennessee, October 28, 1948
  - "The Mission of the Corps of Engineers as Adapted to the Cumberland River Basin," talk before the Old Hickory Engineer's Club, Old Hickory, Tennessee, November 17, 1948
  - "The Wolf Creek Project," talk to be given before the Business Men's Club, Stearns, Kentucky, January 19, 1949
  - "Flood Control for the City of Chattanooga," an address before the Chamber of Commerce, Chattanooga, Tennessee, January 25, 1949
  - "Flood Control for the City of Chattanooga," address before members of the Engineer Club of Chattanooga, Tennessee, February 14, 1949
  - "Comprehensive Improvement of the Cumberland River," talk before American Society of Civil Engineers, February 24, 1949
  - "Corps of Engineers and the Sportsman," address to the League of Kentucky Sportsmen, Frankport, Kentucky, May 16, 1949
  - "Civil Works of the Corps of Engineers, U.S. Army," talk before Kiwanis Club, Florence, Alabama, July 29, 1949
  - "The Wolf Creek Project," talk before the Wayne County, Kentucky Farm Bureau Meeting, August 17, 1949
  - Miscellaneous speech material
- MILITARY FILE, 1934-1955.
  Military engineering reports, military honors and awards, and miscellaneous material, arranged as listed
  - "Differential Leveling on the Great Lakes," by H. V. Canan with Sherman Moore, 1935 (Box 3)
  - "Effects of Master Gauges, Lake Superior - Lakes Huran and Michigan and the Desirability of Changing Datum of Master Gauge on Lake Superior," by H.V. Canan, 1935
  - "Usual Water Fluctuations on Lake Superior, " by H. V. Canan, 1935
  - "Regulation of Lake Superior," by H.V. Canan and members of the board appointed by Division Engineer, October 26, 1934
  - "Historical Report, U.S. Army Corps of Engineers European Theater of Operations"; Troops, Report No. 4, by H. V. Canan, August 1945
  - "Chief Engineers Report on Camouflage Activities in the European Theater of Operations, U.S. Army, " prepared by the Office of the Chief Engineer, November 15, 1945, June 1942 to May 1945
  - "Report of Navigation Possibilities of Port of Monroe, " by H. V. Canan, 1955
  - Honors and Awards
  - Miscellany
- PHOTOGRAPHS
  - 123 photos of H.V. Canan and others at U.S. Military Academy, West Point, 1916-1917 (Envelope A)
  - Photos of war damage, pictures of interest and cultural sites in Western Europe, 1919 (Envelope B)
  - 32 photos depicting H.V. Canan during his military career and miscellaneous and duplicate photos, undated (Envelope C)
  - 191 postwar scenes of Belgium, France and Germany including photos of European tour, 1919; 58 photos of 11th Engineer Regiment in Panama Canal Zone, 1925-1928; 259 photos of Corps of Engineer activities and techniques; Various pictures of vacation and travel (Album fD)
  - 2 troop and 3 portrait photos, undated (Folder m)
  - 2 troop portrait photos, undated (Folder m*dr. 1)